Hi, let's take a look at the high
voltage differential probe. In this case
the Lecroy AP031.
Now, I don't believe this is actually
designed by Lecroy. They just rebadge it
from someone else. I actually forget who
the original manufacturer is of this
thing. And these are an essential tool
for safe operation of your oscilloscope
measuring high volt not only high
voltage stuff, but measuring high common
mode voltages, things like mains power
supplies and things like that, which you
can't do really safely with your regular
oscilloscope
probe. And I've done a whole video on
that. So, click here if you haven't seen
it how not to blow up your oscilloscope.
So, it's a vital thing to understand
that. But one of the ways, of course,
how not to blow up your oscilloscope
when measuring stuff is to use one of
these high voltage differential probes.
It allows you to measure your circuit.
Just hook this onto basically any part
of almost any circuit within reason.
Being a high voltage mains power supply
or whatever other high voltage systems,
three-phase stuff. Doesn't matter what
it is. You can hook these two probes up
to any part of your circuit. By the way,
I've just
I've lost my black one. Hit black
probe hook here. It's around here
somewhere. Anyway, you can hook these up
to any part of your circuit and you will
be completely safe. And then you just
plug the other end, the output. So, this
is the input and you just plug the
output into your oscilloscope. So, it
converts
the differential signal on here, hence
the differential probe, and converts it
to a single-ended signal which goes into
your oscilloscope. Now, these generally
don't have a particularly high
bandwidth. I think this one's about 20
or 30 MHz or something like that. So,
it's, you know, not designed for really
high-speed stuff. But that's not the
point. The point is this that it has not
only a
10:1 range, I eat like a times 10 of
your regular times 10 probe, it divides
your input voltage by 10 that you're
familiar with on your oscilloscope. It's
also got times 100 as well or divide by
100. So, they correspond to a range of
plus minus 70 volts on the one tenth
range and the
1/100 range has plus minus 700 volts and
it's got a common mode voltage of plus
minus 700 volts. So, a brief recap on
what common mode voltage actually means
here. Now, this differential probe, it's
just a differential amplifier. Just like
say an op-amp is a differential
amplifier, but it an op-amp of course
has an a ridiculously high gain. This
one has a relatively small gain of
either times 10 or times 100 to
compensate for the input attenuation
here. So, we can put up to 1,000 volts
RMS across here and well, that's no
problem, but what we we're really
concerned about is this common mode
voltage and this is where you can come a
cropper and I've done that video how to
not to blow up your oscilloscope. What
that common mode voltage means is it's
then referenced to the output here. The
ground of the output, the common of the
output here is connected to your
oscilloscope and that's then connected
through to mains earth. I did that as a
circuit ground, maybe that should be a
mains earth ground, but
then it's the difference in voltage
between your mains earth here and either
of your input voltages. So, I've drawn
that as a voltage source there between
any of those inputs and in the case of
a high voltage differential probe like
this, that can be up to plus minus 700
volts between
the output here. I've drawn an extra
terminal there, I probably shouldn't
have drawn that, and the output and
either of the input terminals. And
that's important when you're measuring
say a mains power supply or something
like that and it is
very high relative to the earth on your
oscilloscope. Now, there's a common
misconception about these high voltage
differential probes. Some people think
that they are isolated probes, i.e. they
have like a transformer in there to
isolate the input from the output like
this, and nothing could be further from
the truth. And we can prove that. The
only thing we need is a multimeter.
Let's measure between say the positive
input and our output ground here, and
I'm not touching it, so it's not my
fingers in the way. Look, 4 meg, okay?
And that's a very consistent 4 meg. I
mean, we can swap that over, so if there
was any like active uh circuitry stuff
going on, you'd expect it to change. But
it doesn't. Look, it's exactly the same.
So, um we've got 4 meg between either of
these inputs here and the output ground.
And we can repeat the exact same thing
for the negative input terminal and the
output ground. You guessed it, it's that
4 meg again. It's very consistent. It is
not isolated. And we can demonstrate
that again using our high voltage mega
here. So, we can select 500 V cuz we've
got a 700 V maximum here, so we don't
want to do 1,000 because, well, we could
blow the ass out of our high voltage
differential probe. They're not
completely infallible, they have ratings
for a reason. So, we're connecting
between the output ground which goes to
our oscilloscope and the input. So,
we'll be able to measure that same
resistance we got before, but instead of
this multimeter only working at, you
know, a a couple of volts, uh this thing
will actually test it at 500 V. So, here
we go. Let's test that, and bingo, we
get the same 4 meg. It is genuinely a
resistance. This thing is not isolated.
So, how does this thing work if it's not
isolated? Well, those resistance
readings might have given you a bit of a
clue, but there's only one way to find
out. You know what we say here on the
EEVblog, don't turn it on, take it
apart. And needless to say, this puppy's
going to have a fair bit of uh shielding
inside there, so
uh we might have to crack that open. In
fact, we might have to uh desolder some
cans to get to the front end.
Practically all of it is shielded. We've
got uh two separate uh sections here, so
our outputs from here, so I'm guessing
that uh this is the input and this is
the output can, and maybe this is just
some uh power supply uh stuff up here,
just uh keeping that separate. But, uh
look, we've got uh at least a couple of
trimmers on there. There's another
couple holes, so maybe they've got some
trimmer caps down the bottom. These are
obviously uh 10-turn pots here for uh
frequency compensation and other sorts
of trimming. And I got this uh can off
here. It was just very lightly uh
soldered onto the sides here, but it
looks like this one has a couple of
solder points down here. These are
actually These tabs are actually from
the can. Thankfully, they're not all
soldered. They just uh tacked it down,
so hopefully I can and uh probably
another couple of points over here, but
anyway, we can start to see the
structure of this thing. Note our high
voltage isolation slots here and here,
here and here like this. So, here's our
input. There's obviously two uh separate
sides to this. This is be like a
symmetrical cuz it's a differential uh
type probe, but I wonder what we're
going to find under here. You might be
able to start guessing. And we're in
like Flynn. We've got ourselves a high
voltage uh
isolation shield here just so that uh
nothing arcs or uh shorts over to the
metal can, of course, and that's
important cuz we've got a lot of
through-hole components here, vertical.
Check it out. It's all a bit
It's all a bit how you doing, but uh
look, numbers rubbed off the chips.
Mongrels, they don't want us to know
what these are. They're probably, you
know, they're they're just op-amps,
right? They're just sort of, you know,
not jelly bean op-amps, but they're not
going to be anything hugely special.
Now, take a look Look what what we've
got here, straddled across the isolation
slot going right down here. These are
all of our high voltage input
components. So, you can see we've got
ourselves some ceramic caps here. These
will be for frequency compensation, as
we'll see. And they've actually heat
shrunk those, maybe to provide
it's not maybe some insulation, but
they're just around them like that. So,
maybe some explosion protection or
something like that. Like they do in
MOVs for uh you know, input MOVs on
multimeters and stuff like that. Um that
might be my guess, but like you know,
there's some resistors in here that are
bent over. So, they're obviously maybe
trying to isolate the leads on there,
but then that's all exposed. And well,
anyway, we've got some resistors here.
It looks messy, but let me try and buzz
it out. Now, you'll actually notice that
it's virtually completely
symmetrical, and that's what you'd
expect from a uh differential front end
like this. So, we got
Oh, no. I thought we had a component
missing in there. Nope. But, let me buzz
all this out and I'll get you a Dave CAD
drawing. And this is designed and or
laid out by Mr. Woo. Good on you, Mr.
Woo. Uh and it's Sapphire. Yes, I
believe that's the original equipment uh
manufacturer. They're the original
designers of this thing, and it's
re-badged under many different names.
So, if I take off that heat shrink, you
can start to see some of the structure
here. Here's our input uh wire, our
negative, our positive uh side of this
circuit's going to be absolutely
identical, of course. And that's in
series with another resistor just end on
end. I love how they've even got the uh
silkscreen symbol down in there for two
end-to-end resistors like that. That's
kind of neat. So, there's two 1 mega
resistors in series, and then that goes
down to another 1 mega resistor, which
then goes over the high voltage
isolation uh slot there and bingo into
another 100 mega resistor down into
there. One meg, two meg, three meg, four
meg. Does that ring a bell? And they've
just got some 6.8
puff caps there. They're all 6.8. Yep.
But they're 1 kilovolt jobs, so they're
high voltage
ceramic caps of course. And these don't
connect anywhere on the underside. So if
we go on the underside there, you can
see that the capacitors don't actually
connect. So it's not like you've got one
capacitor across each resistor there. So
it looks like we've got two
Well, actually one, two, three series
caps across the entire string of those
four one meg resistors. And of course
they could have used one big high
voltage capacitor across there. But hey,
it's not easy to get greater than a 1
kilovolt capacitor. So they used just
used three one kilovolt ones in series,
which gives you your voltage. Likewise
with the resistor, they could have used
just one big ass four meg resistor on
the input there. But hey, you wouldn't
have got the high voltage isolation.
When you string components in series
like this, the voltage ratings of each
resistor and each capacitor add up. So
that is effectively 6.8 divided by
three.
It gives you your capacitance and then
the voltage rating is 3 kilovolts total.
And I do like how they added this little
metal shield here over this
front end where the cables come in. That
just
seals up the gap in the can there for
the cable entry. Someone was thinking.
Mr. Woo was thinking.
Good on you, Mr. Woo. And you don't want
the crap leaking out of your switching
converter. That's why there's two
inductors there and there, L1 and L2.
After putting a bit of spin on that
chip, it turns out someone at the
Taiwanese factory is not very good at
scrubbing off those numbers.
So in true EEVblog style, we'll just
speculate on what's going on here. Let's
give it a go anyway. I won't I don't
plan on really doing a full reverse
engineering to this thing cuz it's a bit
of a pain in the butt and I'm feeling a
bit lazy today anyway. So I just want to
show you that it wasn't an isolated
probe basically and it was using input
dropper resistors, high value dropper
resistors to limit the current and
provide that attenuation ratio on the
front end. So anyway, we've got our
positive and negative input here. We've
got our four meg of resistance here,
four meg worth of resistance here. We've
got some compensation caps around here
and around here. Then the two resistors
in there are going to be the lower end
of the divider. So we've got a four meg
input divider and then it's going to go
over to these two resistors here. Why
they've got three caps? They actually
look to be They're all in parallel. So I
don't know why they've got so many in
parallel. Anyway, we'll have a look at
those values maybe to compensate for
each frequency range, which is a common
technique for like bypassing for example
cuz they'll have a different impedance
characteristic based on their
value and their package size and
everything else. But they're all
identical ceramic capacitors. So that's
a bit unusual having three in parallel.
Anyway, four meg input resistor,
whatever value that is down in there.
Haven't looked at it so that'll give a
fixed division ratio on both the
positive and negative input. This 10
turn trimmer here, that's probably just
used for an offset adjustment thing. And
then we've got some trimmer caps in
there just to trim these two values in
there. And you probably saw the holes in
the metal case, wherever that is. Think
it's over on the other bench. But yeah,
you can get to these after the fact
after you've
soldered it in the metal can to uh trim
those. And then, it looks like you've
got the output of this going over to
here, another output going over here.
That's going into this metal can package
here. Haven't actually looked at that
one yet, but based on the number of pins
there and a common technique used in
scope front ends, which I'm sure we've
seen before uh when I've done scope tear
downs and things like that, that's
probably going to be a matched uh JFET
pair. Very common to use a JFET uh
differential uh you know, roll your own
JFET input amp. So, I reckon that's
what's going on there. That's uh
probably a quad op-amp. And um this
IC up here, what would that be? Okay,
here's our output. It's probably coming
Yeah, it looks like it's coming from
there. So, yeah, yeah, it's coming Yeah,
there's the output coming over there.
So, yep, that's got to be our um output
driver. So, that's converting the
differential output. Um well, I'm not
sure.
Anyway, not sure of the arrangement of
the op-amp there. That's I don't know.
Anyway, um I reckon that's it's
differential all the way probably
through to there and then um
differential to single-ended uh cable
driver. So, that's just like a high-spec
um you know, high slew rate uh low noise
op-amp or something like that um to
drive the output. And uh
Bob's your uncle. We've got another
couple of in here. I don't know
what they'd be doing, maybe some offset
uh stuff, things like that. Um there's
another couple of down in
there, two two of those back-to-back,
but not sure what's maybe with some sort
of I don't know, is there some sort of
current mirror or something going on
there? I'm not entirely sure. Anyway, um
that's going to be the basic
arrangement. And I tell you what, I
think they've tried to actually scrub
the number off that can. That's kind of
what it looks like. The marks don't
really show up.
Is that a 39?
68, is it? So, let's go to Dave CAD
reverse engineering edition. Please
excuse the crudity of this model. I
didn't have time to build it to scale or
to paint it. This is a very, very rough
schematic of what's going on here. In
fact, I'm not actually entirely sure
what's going on here. This chip, which I
thought at first, oh yeah, that's going
to be an op-amp, a quad op-amp. But, I
don't actually think it is. Anyway,
let's have a look at this thing. As
we've seen, we've got our uh four 1 meg
resistors in series and our four 6p8
caps in series for some frequency
compensation on that. And they're all
they're 1,000-V caps of and they're
going into the 25K here and the trimmer,
which is just used for an offset balance
adjustment there. So, you know, we've
got a pretty good division ratio here.
This is why it can survive and measure
all the high voltages. It's basically
differential input. And then, I believe
it's going into a dual matched JFET here
cuz this is very typical front ends.
Although, I couldn't really find any
info on that part number that I saw down
here. It said it was like an N-channel
JFET, but it didn't say it was dual or
anything else.
So, from some obscure company that's
probably not even around anymore.
Anyway,
um
I believe that is a dual JFET input.
That makes sense. We've got some diode
clamping here for input protection. By
the way, these three caps here, 120
puff, 82 puff, and 82 puff, and then
probably a much smaller trimmer cap
value here just to trim the frequency
compensation on this thing after it's
all assembled in the metal cans,
everything else is on. You get in there
and hold your tongue at the right angle
and tweak these, tweak your balance
adjustments, and there's a couple of
other pots in here which I haven't uh
reverse engineered and uh showin. So,
it's kind of unusual that they've got
the three in parallel. Not entirely sure
why they're actually doing that. Um
they're all the same type of ceramic.
So, maybe they're just trying to
get a tighter tolerance or something by
putting the three in parallel like that.
That's all I can think of so that the
trimmer has a better
uh more accurate, more controllable
adjustment range perhaps. Anyway, going
into two JFETs and then um after that,
I'm not sure what that puppy there's
doing, but it by just looking at the
pinout and everything else, it doesn't
seem to be an op-amp. So, what I think
it is and because it just didn't make
sense in this sort of arrangement here
to have an op-amp directly um on the
output here. It's not that one. Forget
that for a second. A differential JFET
front end like this usually needs some
extra transistors here and usually
formed a forming a current uh source
down here. So, that's a usual
arrangement. So, I think my guess is
that that puppy's actually one of those
uh transistor array uh chips and I
couldn't make heads or tails of the
number. The number the partial number
that I got off that certainly didn't
make sense in terms of a quad uh op-amp
part number. So, I believe that's some
form of uh transistor array array. They
were uh quite common back in the day.
You can still get them in various forms.
TI and other uh companies make them and
stuff like that um and lots of obscure
uh providers back in the day. Uh matched
transistor uh things. The reason that
they're good is because they're matched
on the same die. If you try and do a
discrete front end like this with all
separate two separate JFETs and then
separate uh bipolar usually bipolar uh
transistors, it won't be uh JFETs. So,
these will be BJTs in here. So, a whole
like I'm missing a whole section of
circuitry there. I mean, this is not
just two resistors and a current you
know, there's going to be
you know, like usually these have like
uh four like five or six transistors
usually in a current in a differential
configuration with the emitters tied
together and stuff like that. Anyway, I
reckon that's
what that puppy is doing there. So that
makes sense and then the output the
differential output is then going over
to this puppy which has had the number
rubbed off so I don't I can't even get a
partial on that one.
So that'd be converting the differential
into the single ended driver to drive
your coax over here and that's about all
she wrote. There's a couple of other
transistors in there. I haven't bothered
to
reverse engineer all that. There's a
couple of other trimmer adjustments in
here which are probably well don't this
one might be output gain for example and
this one here might be current source
adjustment. So I reckon that's what's
going on there. So if anyone actually
has a complete schematic of this thing,
I'd really like to see it. Anyway, this
wasn't really a 100% reverse engineering
video. It was just to show you what's
inside one of these differential probes
and then they're not actually isolated.
They the reason that they're safe is
because they use these resistors in
series like this and you're protected.
So if you're holding on to the output
and the grounded output like this and
you've got hundreds of volts 500 volts
floating around in here relative to the
ground that you're holding on to you're
pretty darn safe because you've got four
meg in either lead like this and you've
got multiple capacitors in series as
well. You know, like you if you just had
the one cap in there you could get a
single fire then it might render it a
bit unsafe. It could go through the 25k
to ground and your output, you know,
this is your ground reference output
here so that could you know, if you're
holding on to that doing whatever then
you know, it could be a problem. But
these are very safe probes just by
nature of the four one meg resistors in
series and the high voltage isolation
slots and the rated caps and everything
else. So, Bob's your uncle. It's how it
works. It's just a basic JFET
differential amplifier with a big
attenuator on the front end. And just
for kicks, there's inside the DC to DC
converter and they rubbed the number off
yet again.
Why? Protect a crummy discrete DC to DC
converter.
Give me a break. And we'll just have a
quick squeeze at what rails we've got
here. Of course,
nothing's marked on here. There's no
voltage rails, no ground points marked.
But of course, for ground, you almost
always take the ground plane on Well,
the plane on there, the main plane, it's
almost certainly going to be ground. And
then, as I think I mentioned before,
we've got the two inductors there and
there. I think this is only going to be
giving out There we go, 9 and 1/2 volts.
And the other one should be negative
similar. Yep, -9.5.
So, there you have it. That's inside the
LeCroy AP031 / Sapphire 9001
differential high voltage differential
probe. So, I hope you found that
interesting just how these things work.
With the front end, I mean, the exact
reverse engineering details aren't
aren't a huge big deal. But the fact
that it uses those two big resistive
dividers with a differential FET front
end, that's what we wanted to know.
Rather interesting little beast this one
is. Ancient.
I don't know the date on this one.
They've rubbed off all the bloody codes
on there. Anyway, this design must date
back a long time. I got this one back
when I was still working at Siracell, I
think. So, 5 and 1/2 years EEVblog
full-time, 4 years at Altium, you know,
it's probably a good 10 years ago I got
this and it was an old model back then.
It might be a more modern variant these
days cuz it is pretty how you doing.
It's all through-hole design. I'd be
surprised if they haven't done a new
modernized version of it or something
like that, but it's probably still
identical. But, you probably wouldn't
manufacture still manufacture that one
today. I would modernize it with some
surface mount stuff at least just to you
know just to make it neater and tidier
and get your production cost down. But,
the design would still be as valid as it
was back then. And well, you know,
there's some
like the fit front end might have gone
obsolete or something like that. The
transistor array might have gone
obsolete. You might, you know, modernize
those or something like that. But, the
basic technique and everything else
would remain very much similar. And
there's other ones on the market as
well. You can get them for like 300
bucks on eBay these days. Not this
particular model, but there's another
one. Actually, I see I think I can get
my hands on one of those. It'll be
interesting to do a a teardown of the
cheap $300 eBay one. And see Anyway,
hope you enjoyed it. Catch you next
time.
Hi. I just read a post on the EE Vblog
forum where somebody was asking about
the oscilloscope probes and how
they can be potentially dangerous if you
hook this ground lead up to the wrong
point in your circuit. You can blow up
your circuit. You can blow up your
scope. Bang! And it really is a big trap
for young players. And I've mentioned it
before, but they wanted to know exactly
under what circumstances that could
happen.